Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
My name is Marko.
My name is Catherine
and we have an unusual
lesson for you today. It's more about
writing than about speaking. That's right.
Well, many times we have
to write emails and if we're
working in a sales environment, we may need
to write an email to a potential client.
Alright, so we're
going to learn what is
appropriate and what
is not in today's lesson.
Let's take a listen to our dialogue.
Melanie, can you help
me with something?
We need to finalize the
account with the Mexican
Embassy and I need some advice on
phrasing this letter correctly in English.
Sure Tracy, let me
just get my laptop.
Right, all set. Okay, so
to whom it may concern,
I am writing, um,
Tracy, I think that's a
little too formal. I know
you want to be polite
but you've already made contact with them
so in English you can be a bit more relaxed
in the opening. Okay, more relaxed. Got it.
Hey Sally, what's up? It's Tracy here, just
okay Tracy. Now
it's too relaxed.
You still got to show some
respect. How about starting
with Dear Miss Cooper? I'm writing to
confirm, great, okay. Dear Miss Cooper, I'm
writing to confirm the
final quotation for the
full page, back cover,
color advertisements,
you requested for the spring issue of Viola
magazine. That's great. The final costing,
including advert design and
production comes to 45,600 R&B.
We want payment 10 working days
before publication or
we will cancel the ad.
Thanks for-- Oh, okay,
back up a second Tracy.
That's too direct.
Can I suggest you say,
please note that the
final payment is due to
working weeks before publication, you don't
want to offend her. Oops, okay, you're
right. Then I can just end
with all the best, Tracy.
Hmm, maybe I'd play it safe
and just finish with yours sincerely.
That's more professional.
Oh, Melanie, you're a lifesaver.
Thank you. All right, we're back. So now
let's take a look at some of that vocab we
heard on language
takeaway. Language takeaway.
We have some
wonderful adjectives today.
The first one that I wanted
to discuss, Marco, is formal.
Formal, that's right.
We want to be a little bit
more formal when we're
writing someone. We
don't really know too much.
That's right, but we have to be careful
because sometimes you can be too formal.
So what exactly does
formal mean? So if you write a
formal email, it's very
proper, very respectful
so proper in the way that you wouldn't use
colloquial terms or phrasal verbs that, you
know, like that you would
use with your friends.
No, a good example
is, is writing to a
lawyer or a judge. You
want to use formal language.
Even with a teacher,
you might use more
formal language. But with
a friend, you don't have to.
That's something
else. That's right.
So when you're writing
something that's formal,
it's important to be polite
as well. Now what is polite?
Right. So you want to be formal. You want
to be serious and you want to be polite.
You want to show respect. You
want to be nice, basically. That's right.
And so people can often
be described as polite.
He's very polite or
she's not polite at all.
Right. And you know,
when I was a little
kid, my mom used to say
it's very important to be polite.
Always say thank you and you're welcome
when you're talking to other people.
That's right. And that's
one way of being polite.
Now, also when we
are describing the
way that you speak to someone or the
way that you write, you can be very direct.
Now, being direct
means that you say exactly
what you want or exactly
what you're thinking.
Okay. So maybe if we're talking to
this company, you say, hi, I want this.
I will pay this much.
Thank you. Bye. Right.
That's maybe two directions.
So sometimes you need to
be a little less direct and
say nice things in an email.
That's right. So maybe you want to
say to someone that you don't really like
the clothes they're
wearing. Right.
And you say, hey, do you
like my new shirt? And if you're
very direct, you would
say, no, I think it's very ugly.
I hate it. Right.
That's too direct.
So maybe you would
say, I don't really think
it suits you very well.
Or I think a different
color would be better
on you. That's right.
So that's being a
little bit less direct.
Now, obviously, if you're
too direct with someone,
you may offend
that person. All right.
To offend is a verb. And
to offend someone means
to say something that makes them unhappy or
upset or even angry. So going back to the
same example of the
shirt, if you say, I think
that shirt is very ugly, that
person might be offended.
Gosh. Or maybe if you say, you know, I
think people with brown hair are so ugly.
And there's someone next to me with brown
hair, they say, oh, I'm offended. Right.
I'm not ugly, but I have
brown hair. That's right.
Okay. So you don't want to offend anyone
by being too direct. Or you don't want to
have anyone feel
offended. Now, for our last
phrase here on language
takeaway, we have
towards the end of the
dialogue, Tracy, Tracy,
thanks, Melanie, by
saying you are a lifesaver.
Thank you. Okay.
So don't be confused.
There is also a candy
called lifesavers.
And she's not calling her a candy.
Right. She's saying, wow, thank you.
You really helped me. Okay.
So when someone helps
you a lot, you can call
them a lifesaver. Right. Marco,
what exactly is the object?
The lifesaver?
If you've ever been on a
boat, you see this big orange
circle that is used to
throw into the water
to help someone to
prevent them from drowning.
That is called a lifesaver.
Okay. So I'm drowning.
I'm having a hard time writing this email.
I do not know what to say. Marco, you come
and help me. I can say, oh, wow. Thank you
so much. You're a lifesaver. That's exactly
right. All right. So
we've taken a look at
five keywords there.
Why don't we take a listen
to our dialogue again and
we'll be back with fluency builder.
Melanie, can you help
me with something?
We need to finalize the
account with the Mexican
Embassy and I need
some advice on phrasing
this letter correctly
in English. Sure, Tracy.
Let me just get my
laptop. Right. All set.
Okay. So to whom it
may concern, I am writing
Tracy, I think that's
a little too formal.
I know you want to be
polite, but you've already
made contact with them. So in English, you
can be a bit more relaxed in the opening.
Okay. More relaxed.
Got it. Hey, Sally.
What's up? It's Tracy
here. Just okay, Tracy.
Now it's too relaxed. You've
still got to show some respect.
How about starting with dear
Miss Cooper? I'm
writing to confirm. Great.
Okay. Dear Miss Cooper,
I'm writing to confirm
the final quotation for the full page back
cover color advertisement you requested for
the spring issue
of Viola magazine.
That's great. The final
costing, including adverb design
and production,
comes to 45,600 R&B.
We want payment 10
working days before publication
or we will cancel the
ad. Thanks for... Okay.
Back up a second,
Tracy. That's too direct.
Can I suggest you say,
please note that the final
payment is due to working
weeks before publication.
You don't want to offend her. Oops. Okay.
You're right. Then I can just end with all
the best, Tracy. Hmm.
Maybe I'd play it safe
and just finish with
yours sincerely. That's
more professional.
Oh Melanie, you're a lifesaver. Thank you.
So today in fluency
builder, we have a number
of phrases you can use
when you're writing an email.
Some of them are
very polite and formal.
very informal or casual.
Now, this first phrase Marco
is very, very formal, right?
That's right. We start our letter by
stating to whom and may concern.
All right. To whom? It may
concern. Remember that M there.
This is a very formal phrase and
we're going to take it as a phrase.
This is how you begin a
formal letter. That's right.
Usually you start this
letter if it's directed
to maybe a company
or someone not specific.
You don't know
that person's name.
And you're just saying
whoever's reading this letter,
whoever it concerns. That's
right. Well, I could say dear Marco.
Right. But in this case, maybe I don't
know who the name of the person
I am writing this
email to. Mm hmm.
It's a big company.
There are many people.
So if you don't know who
you're writing to in a company
or in an organization, you
say to whom it may concern.
That's right. Okay.
Now we started very formal.
Melanie said, I think it's
a little bit too formal. Maybe we should be
more relaxed. So Tracy says, okay, got it.
So how about Hey Sally? What's up?
What's up? Okay. What's up? What's up?
Is the kind of thing I say with
my friends? You know, hey
Marco, what's up?
Right. But I would never
say this in a formal situation with a boss
or with a, you know, an employer or with a,
more serious situation. Exactly. Especially
if you're writing an email to a client.
You don't really want to
say what's up. No, never.
So remember, this
is spoken English with
your friends, but not
something you would write.
So the key here is that you
have to show some respect.
Okay. So that's
another great phrase.
You show some
respect. All right.
So the key here is that this
is the verb is to show, right?
Not to give. You want to
show respect to someone.
Well, how do you show respect?
Well, the way that
you act, your behaviors.
So if I'm polite and I
say, you know, Mr and
miss and thank you and
please, these are ways
to show respect.
That's right. That's right.
So that's the way that
you are being respectful.
You are showing respect
by being very polite.
For example, in Japan,
it is common to take
your shoes off when
you go to a friend's home
in their house in order
to show respect to them.
That's right. Very good.
Now, as we continue writing
the letter towards the end,
we wanted to play it safe and just write
yours sincerely to close the letter off.
All right. So this
phrase, play it safe.
What does this mean? When
we're talking about making
a decision or taking a
risk, we want to play it safe.
We want to use
the less risky option.
All right. So the key here
is that the verb is to play.
Play it safe. This means that, yeah, there's
maybe a risky option and a safe option,
and it's better to
take the safe option.
That's right. That's right. So that's
the way that you would use this phrase,
say, play it safe to make a
decision that doesn't have
too much risk or that you
know that will work very well.
And to close things off,
another option to end the letter,
we could say all
the best, all the best,
Tracy, all the best
comma, Tracy. All right.
So this is a way to end the letter. You can
say sincerely or best, but it's a very nice
way to end if you
just say all the best.
And then you say, you
know, after that, you have
a comma and then
you sign your name.
That's right. All right.
Let's listen to our dialogue
one last time and we'll be
back to talk a little bit more.
Melanie, can you help
me with something?
We need to finalize the
account with the Mexican
Embassy, and I need some advice on
phrasing this letter correctly in English.
Sure, Tracy. Let me just
get my laptop. Right.
All set. Okay. So to whom it may concern,
I am writing, um, Tracy, I think that's a
little too formal. I know
you want to be polite,
but you've already
made contact with them.
So in English, you can be a
bit more relaxed in the opening.
Okay, more relaxed. Got it.
Hey, Sally. What's
up? It's Tracy here.
Just okay, Tracy.
Now it's too relaxed.
You've still got to show some
respect. How about starting
with dear Miss Cooper?
I'm writing to confirm.
Great. Okay. Dear
Miss Cooper, I'm writing
to confirm the final quotation for the full
page back cover, color advertisement, you
requested for the spring
issue of Viola magazine.
That's great. The
final costing, including
advert design and production
comes to 45,600 R&B.
We want payments
10 working days before
publication, or we
will cancel the ads.
Thanks for. Okay.
Back up a second, Tracy.
That's too direct. Can I
suggest you say, please
note that the final
payment is due to working
weeks before publication, you don't want
to offend her. Oops. Okay. You're right.
Then I can just end with
all the best, Tracy. Hmm.
Maybe I'd play it safe
and just finish with
yours sincerely. That's more professional.
Oh, Melanie, you're a lifesaver. Thank you.
So talking about ending
formal emails or emails
that you're writing
to clients, colleagues,
we can say sincerely in
your name, sincerely Marco.
You can say all the
best, best regards.
Now I've noticed that
some people who aren't
a native English
speaker, sometimes they
will close a letter, maybe
even a formal letter,
saying yours truly
Marco, for example.
Is that really appropriate for
a business setting or a client?
I would not use yours truly.
Maybe if you're trying
to build a relationship
with your client, and
you're very honest,
but it seems to me to be
very personal, very romantic.
Yes, yours truly. So I would say in
that case, use sincerely or kind regards
regards, which are a
little bit more professional
and less emotional. If you
want to have a romantic
letter, you can say,
you know, all my love
or love or yours truly
or yours faithfully.
This is a very important
topic, I think, because many
times in school, we do
learn how to write letters,
but usually they are
more personal letters,
and so we memorize that
usually at the end of the
email or the end of
the letter, you say yours,
Marco, or yours truly
Marco. And although it
is correct, it's not really appropriate
for a professional setting. That's right.
So just as a reminder, if
you're signing off your email or
your letter and you're
at an office, you're in
your company, you want
to say best or best regards,
or some of the things that
we talked about here today.
Very good. All right.
So if you have any
questions or any other doubts,
you can always find us at EnglishPod.
com. And we'll see
you guys there. Bye.